let's look at the solution for our BTB
quiz the question was which b2b entries
is used for a particular PC it might
seem easy because we need 10 bits to
index into this BT B so we will just
take the least significant 10 bits of
this PC and index into the BTB with that
however note that instructions are fixed
size 4 bytes and word aligned which
means that not all addresses are
possible for the program counter if you
now look at what would happen if we use
the least significant 10 bits to index
into the BTB we would see that the entry
number 0 would be used an instruction
can have the least significant n bits be
all 0 entry number 1 however requires
the least significant 10 bits to be 0 0
0 0 0 1 and that entry cannot be used
because the instructions are word
aligned as we said addresses such as all
zeros and then just 1 are not possible
basically all addresses actually need to
be not only even but also divisible by 4
so if you take the lowermost bits that
means that the only possible instruction
addresses are of the form something
something something and then the least
significant two bits are 0 that means
that we are really using only every 4th
entry in our BTB pretty much of the
1,024 entry BTB we are really using only
256 entries which is a huge waste so in
this case what should happen is we
should not use the least significant 10
bits and instead we use these 10 bits so
that the least significant bits that can
be different among instructions
basically these bits are always 0 so
they're just going to waste entries we
need to take the least significant 10
bits that are still different among
different instructions so in this case
our instruction has bits C is 1 1 0 0 0
is 0 0 0 0 B is 1 0 1 1 we're gonna
ignore these two bits and take the
next one two three four five six seven
eight nine ten bits so this is the index
into our BTB and now let's convert that
to hex this will be the first hex digit
so it would be three this would be the
next hex digit so it would be C and this
would be two so we are talking about the
entry number to c3